When we think of German rail, we imagine
the pinnacle of rail transport. The best
trains and tracks ever. A system so
punctual you can set your watch to it.
An industry leader carrying the torch of
European rail. This idea is so
entrenched in our culture that even the
Big Bang Theory included it in a scene
where Sheldon is like, "My bowel
movements run like a German train
schedule."
>> But you may or may not be surprised to
learn that this is not how Germans think
of German rail or anyone else who has
used it more than once. Because, and it
pains me to say this, but German rail is
utter. Train cancellations, breakdowns,
delays, decaying infrastructure, filthy
stations, utter chaos. Viking stung. The
AC doesn't work, the toilet is clogged,
and you're trying to get on, but someone
walled off the [__] door. Meanwhile,
punctuality in long-distance traffic is
reaching historic lows. Currently
hovering around 60%. In late 2025, going
as low as 51.5%.
Leonard, my bowel movements run like a
German train schedule. I haven't been on
the toilet for 5 days. It can come at
any moment. I have no idea when.
Leonard, help me. I can't leave the
house. I'm trapped. As of 2026, German
rail is in shambles. Now, some people
might butt in and say that this is still
better than in my country. Yeah, great.
Where do you live? Albania. Yeah, of
course it's better. But everything is
relative. Like, imagine your tap water
being slightly yellow and smelling
funny. It's nothing dangerous, but you
still complain about it. But then some
genius comes along and says, "Well, did
you know that some people in central
Africa don't even have running water in
their house?" Yeah, great. But I'm not
some people and I don't live in central
Africa. I live in a developed country. I
pay taxes, [music] lots of taxes. I pay
my bills and so I want clean water in my
[__] tap as a civilizational minimum.
Same thing with [music] rail. Actually,
it's worse considering that Germany is
Europe's biggest and strongest economy.
You're the richest and most powerful,
and this is what you were able to
accomplish. 60% punctuality, rotting
infrastructure, aging rolling stock,
filthy stations, that's [music] it,
mediocre. And it's all because of
politics. To understand what the issue
is, picture your average aging postwar
centrist politician. They don't believe
in much. They don't have any particular
strong beliefs about anything. They have
no particular ideology or vision. The
only thing they are able or willing to
do is to keep the system going somehow.
To be fair, for most of their lives,
they've been living in a world where
that's all they had to do. Pakamericana,
the Soviet Union was done. Western
neoliberal capitalism reigned supreme
globally and so [music] on. So really
all they had to do was to keep the
machine running. And back then it really
looked like their world will be the end
all be all. New modern technology
started appearing like airplanes that
weren't dangerous or cars that would
reliably start in the morning. Look at
that sleek modern bus, that car, that
sleek modern airplane. How cool they
are, how new they are. Now compare them
to the old and busted trains and trams
chugging on rails from the previous
century. Obviously the future is roads,
airports, cars, and airplanes. Maybe
buses. And once again, in their defense,
back then it really looked like that's
going to be the future. Wait, what's
that? Japan built highspeed rail,
proving that rail is actually the future
of long-distance transport. Ah, we're
just going to ignore that. But such
politicians in Europe couldn't just rip
up all their tracks and kill rail
transport like Americans did. voters in
Europe would not have liked that. So
instead, they just started defunding and
neglecting rail except for a few
important lines that served as a
showcase kind of [music] around which
the entire system was slowly decaying.
But hey, oh my god, look at this shiny
new train, the Intercity Express.
[music] It's basically an airplane on
tracks. Seriously, things start making
so much sense once you realize that
those postwar boomer politicians could
only think in terms of airplanes and
cars. So when designers showed them the
IC1's interior, they were like, "hm, I'm
getting I'm getting airplane vibes from
this." Great. Approved. So while the
postwar political class labored on
making rail service look and feel more
like airplanes and or luxury cars, the
only things they ever knew, the rest of
the system was slowly decaying. Switches
and sidetracks were removed because they
were not efficient enough. So let's just
rip them up. We save on maintenance and
so rail will make a profit. Everything
has to make a profit. It's the 1990s.
The name of the game is generic
skyscrapers, airplanes, cars, and the
line going up. Imagine like an endless
vapor wave music video. Basically,
that's the world they wanted. But then
one little global oil shock later, we
started realizing that trains were
actually pretty great. In fact, when
built properly, they are superior to
cars and airplanes. If only someone had
proven this already. So, all right,
German rail starts investing in rolling
stock. The Deutschan ticket comes out,
providing unlimited countrywide train
travel at a bargain price. People flock
to rail, passenger numbers are at
constant growth, and then the cracks
start appearing. As traffic volume
grows, punctuality and reliability take
a nose dive, mostly in long-distance
traffic. Local traffic is still fine by
and large, though only due to shorter
distances and the sheer volume of
transit. Long-distance rail though is
screwed, producing the aforementioned
bottom of the barrel lows of 51.5%
punctuality with trains being quote
unquote punctual as long as their delay
does not exceed 6 minutes. So what went
wrong? Why is this happening? The short
answer because they took all those new
traffic volumes and threw them on a
decrepit, underfunded, crumbling network
which was meant for half that volume
back in 1965
when it was still new. It's hard to
maintain a constant frequent service of
long-distance local and freight services
on tracks built half a century ago with
most of the equipment being decades past
its original intended service life.
Because of that, you get things like
what happened with the Deutschan Tact,
an [music] integrated clock face
scheduled timetable for the entire
country. If you don't know what that
does, basically it makes all the trains
be very punctual, the schedule very
reliable, and real travel very
convenient. Everything is connected to
everything. Frequencies are high,
everything is on time. It's what the
Swiss have and their punctuality is the
best in Europe at 94.1%.
And for them, a punctual train is one
with less than 3 minutes of delay, not
six like Deutschean. Hey, do you know
what else is Swiss? Proton Mail, the
sponsor of today's video. Are you
looking to break free from American big
tech to not have all your data flow
through the computers of Silicon Valley
tech oligarchs? Well, now here's Proton
Mail to the rescue. Proton Mail is a
privacy focused encrypted email service
keeping your personal data safe. Not
even Proton can see what's in your
emails, as opposed to services like
Gmail, where your emails may or may not
be used to train AI. Proton Mail is
funded entirely by its user base,
meaning they have no incentive to sell
off your data to third parties.
Migrating from Gmail is easy. It takes
30 seconds to move everything from your
old account. If you want to keep your
old Gmail, that's not an issue at all.
With Easy Switch, you can have your mail
forwarded to your new Proton account
automatically. Proton is also a European
provider. Therefore, as I've mentioned,
it's an alternative to Silicon Valley
big tech oligarchs and their
increasingly predatory services. Go to
proton.me/adam
somethingthing to get started with
Proton Mail for free. Their service is
always free with optional paid plans for
additional features and benefits. That's
proton.me/adam
something. Thank you for checking out
Proton Mail. So, the Deutschanduct was
envisioned for Germany as a way to
create a worldclass rail system rivaling
that of Switzerland. Plans were to enact
it in 2030, but because of the state of
German rail infrastructure, it had to be
postponed a little bit by 40 [__]
years. Deutschanduct [music]
coming in 2070. Brought to you by the
country with Europe's strongest economy.
Because of the constant problems with
German rail, Swiss railways actually
started restricting the entry of German
trains. The rule is if an IC is late, it
does not go further than the first
station past the border. From there,
passengers are free to use local Swiss
railways trains to their destinations.
Because German rail is so unreliable, it
actually started messing with the
meticulously designed Swiss train
schedule, which is beyond embarrassing.
Of course, when your rail system is so
[__] that your neighbors stop letting in
your trains. Speaking of,
now when we think of German rail, we
usually think of rail within Germany.
Now, you could say, well, duh, it's
German rail, but it's not that simple.
Austrian railbe has an impressive
international network. Their trains go
everywhere, even to Italy. Despite the
fact that, as they say, it's easier to
send the train to the moon than to
Italy. German rail is much bigger than
Austrian rail. They have more and more
diverse rolling stock, a larger network,
more employees, and they are
strategically situated in the very
center of Europe, directly bordering
nine countries. Historically, Germany
has had a large international network,
including via the Trans Europe Express
program. Now that was first class only
sort of a rare premium service but the
TE network and their trains were the
precursors for things like the IC deja
bay railjet and so on. When the TE
network began shrinking it did so
because its lines were replaced by more
frequent services that also included
things like secondass. [music] Now back
during the 70s and 80s you could just
get on an international train in Berlin
and travel as far as Buchares Romania.
Oh no no no not this again.
So yeah, German international rail has
historically been pretty great. So what
does it look like today? How does the
richest and most powerful country in
Europe with the largest rail network
handle its international passenger rail
after the fall of the Berlin Wall open
internal borders, no border checks in
the Shenhen era of free movement? Well,
here is the long-distance rail network
of Germany. A very impressive system
despite the German political elitees
best efforts. Now let's see their
international connections.
Yeah. Ah, but wait, let's also delete
seasonal and very infrequent lines.
There we go. Three or less trains per
day per direction is not a real rail
service after all. It's a Disneyland
ride for people who chose the train path
on their autism tech tree like I did.
Ah, but let's be even more precise here
and include only those international
connections run by German rails own
rolling stock. There we go. Deutschean.
[__] yeah. [music] These scanned few
international connections running to
this country in the very center of
Europe are mostly run by other
countries. Connections towards Poland
are run by Pape. Denmark runs its own
fleet of Talgo trains running as DSB
Euro cities to Czecha. It's officially a
cooperation between Chescadrai, Czech
railways and Deutschean which consisted
of D slapping a sticker on the side of
each car and then Deutschean started
[__] with Chescadi, stopping trains
on the border, not letting them into the
country because of some alleged minor
technical defects on some of the cars.
what those 3 to 400 passengers will do
on the border during a summer heat wave
with the next already overloaded train
coming in 2 hours only. Well, that
sounds like a Czech railways problem.
Hungarian railways also runs trains on
this route between Budapest and Hamburg.
Hey everyone, just jumping in here
during the editing process with a quick
correction. Hungaria trains are no
longer run using Hungarian railways
rolling stock as of December 2025. Czech
railways took over fully with brand new
railjet sets and thank God for that. My
condolences to all those who got
scoliosis from those goddamn seats.
Their rolling stock is [__] But hey, at
least it's there. Hungarian railways
actually eats losses on this line, but
they do it anyway as public service.
This being essentially a favor to
Deutschean. And then Deutschean started
[__] with them too. Having discovered
a technical defect at the border, they
once again barred it from entering. So,
dear hundreds of passengers, get the
hell out onto the platform because one
of the cars had a non-functional AC and
one of the windows had its upper part
slightly broken. Well, should they just,
I don't know, empty out that one car and
lock it down? No. Let's just terminate
the entire [__] train because why
not? Things got so out of control, the
Czech Ministry of Transportation had to
intervene, officially asking Deutschean
to let the trains go, at least until
Dresden, the first major German city on
the route just on the other side of the
border, so we don't have hundreds of
people milling around this small border
station, causing chaos by trying to get
on the next already overloaded train. So
Deutschean said, "Sure, fine. Even if
there's a problem, we'll let the trains
go until Dresden. We won't stop them on
the border anymore. We promise." And
then they did it again anyway. But hey,
if you think that's bad, then may I
present to you the Prague Munich
International Rail Line, brought to you
by the Free State of Bavaria. Actually,
you know what? Nah, [__] it. We're doing
this.
Bavaria is one of the richest regions in
Germany and in Europe. They are
Switzerland outside Switzerland. And
what do they do with their immense
wealth and prosperity? [music] Where do
they invest it? Not in rail, I tell you
that much. If you want a picture of
Bavaria, you can get it like so. Imagine
a bunch of syrupy sweet buolic
gingerbread houses on the Windows XP
background. [music] Add highways
everywhere. Also like two cities that
are basically enclaves of young people
as last desperate bastions of actual
living culture. Then throw a bunch of
fat disgusting boomers in giant luxury
cars everywhere. Then dows everything
with beer. Welcome to Bayern. When I
first traveled through Bavaria by train,
I was very surprised. Not in a good way.
We have this region with high-tech
industry, a global leader with
incredible wealth and all. And
meanwhile, here I am slowly chugging
along a single track on electrified rail
line on a train built half a century
ago. As I look outside, I see a rich
boomer zooming past the eight lane
perfectly flat concrete highway. It's
Marco Zod, the emperor of Bavaria,
sitting in a black BMW SUV larger than a
Panzer 2. His ass fused to the leather
seat, equipped with heating and cooling
and other technology that would have
been featured on Star Trek 30 years ago.
>> Take the easy way out. Literally go to
the seat comfort app, find comfort exit,
and activate it. Switch off the driving
ready state, unfasten, and enjoy your
seat automatically moving back for a
comfortable [music] exit. All the while,
Bavarian Rail is going to [__] even
more so than the rest of the country.
But hey, at least those BMW cars are
very comfortable. Oh, wait. What's this?
Oh my god, these people are [__]
stereotypes. And the single track, slow,
unelectrified rail line in question, the
one that I took, is actually the Prague
Munich International mainline. What the
[__] These people do not give a [__]
To check credit here, they've been
wanting to redo the line for a long
time, but they were universally met with
complete disinterest from the German
side. Verines, there is a highway
already. Checks are about to upgrade the
line, their half anyway.
Electrification, ETCs, 200 km/h. But
because of Germany's lack of interest,
they won't add the required capacity.
Parts of the line will be single track
and the end section will only receive a
lesser overhaul. Because why build it
out fully if it won't be used fully for
the next 20 years? Because the capacity
is missing on the other side and will
continue doing so until members of the
current Bavarian political elite reach
[music] the end of their natural
lifespans. Anyway, that's Bavaria for
you. German rail as a whole though is
not much better especially when
Deutschean, the German state and other
giant corporations start to collude.
A couple of years ago, German rail came
up with a wonderful idea. They applied
for and received funding for a
revolutionary new freight car brake
system, so-called LL blocks or whisper
brakes. The nice thing about them is
that they are very silent. They are
advanced, modern, great, good,
environmentally friendly, and it just
happens to be only produced by Kora
Bremza, a major German corporation. So,
step one, Germany asks for and receives
EU funding for new train brakes, which
are only produced by one German company.
Step two, the Godard base tunnel
derailment, causing €150 million worth
of damage and shutting down the most
important piece of Swiss rail
infrastructure for more than a year.
brought to you by German federal level
corruption. The problem with the LL
blocks or whisper brakes is that they
overheat leading to increased material
fatigue over time or even fires. But
hey, at least Bremza made a lot of cash
with them. Next to stuff like this,
others look like mere tiny details like
Debe Cargo operating in open violation
of European law about forbidden state
aid for 20 years and only now deciding
that it's time to play by the rules.
rules which Germany helped draft and
specifically agreed to. [gasps] What a
[__] mess. And by the way, the
Deutschan ticket didn't even work that
well, even when it only cost €9 for
unlimited national public transit use.
Car traffic decreased only by 4 to 5%,
but train delays increased by 30%.
Because people didn't really change cars
for trains. They just started to take
the train more often on the rotting
dilapidated rail system designed to deal
with half that load. [music] And that's
when [__] really started going downhill.
Now, as of late, Germany began to
invest, or rather reinvest into its rail
system. It kind of sort of started
crawling out of the pit, which is nice.
But to achieve lasting results, we need
someone else in charge. Up until
recently, Germany has been led by a
particularly uncarismatic Burger King
manager. But maybe even that [music]
would be beyond his leadership
capabilities. But now, instead of him,
we have an arrogant, snooty bank manager
with great, popular, and timely ideas
such as ending the German welfare state
in the middle of a cost of living
crisis. So yeah, get ready for the
fourth Reich or something. And if you
have the right to vote, do vote for
Dinka or Dun, the left or the Greens.
You get to avert the rise of Twitter
fascism and also get leaders who are
able to view the world in terms of
actual public transit, not just cars and
airplanes. Thank you for watching my tie
raid against German rail. If you like my
content, please consider supporting me
on Patreon or become a channel member
here on YouTube. I also have a tabletop
war game in the works. The link to our
play testing Discord is in the
description as well. Thank you for
watching once again and I'll be seeing
you next time. [music]
[music]